Today I'm going to cover primarily
preference optimization and I think a is
going to cover some things related to
reasoning. So let's get started.
Um
I guess like the one clear trend in the
last 5 to 10 years has been that we've
been like building larger and larger
models and we've been putting far more
compute into them. This is like an ever
very consistent trend and if you're
familiar with or if you have like some
people are even making predictions about
like AGI 2027 and they are like
predicting that we're going to keep
putting more and more floatingoint
operations into these models.
But the question today we're going to
try to answer is how do we get from like
these large language models which are
pre-trained to predict text and get
these like really nice chatbots that
some of them you might have used. So I'm
going to very briefly talk about this is
not an NLP course and you should
probably like take one if you're
interested in learning more about
pre-training. It's a very very deep
topic but I'm going to quickly touch
upon what we learn in pre-training and
why like that doesn't necessarily like
translate into the kind of chat bots um
we use. So in pre-training large
language models they are trained on
these gigantic corpus of internet texts
and the way they're trained is roughly
predicting what the next word or the
next token in the sentence is going to
be. So for example, if you have a
sentence Stanford University is located
in blank California. So like the model
will learn to predict what this text is.
And you can imagine then you're learning
to predict this text. Um you're learning
a lot of facts. You're learning a lot of
trivia, but you're also starting to
learn something about the syntax of the
of how like language operates.
And we can we can look at many different
examples here. Iro went to the kitchen
to make some tea. Standing next to Iro,
Zuko pondered his destiny. Zuko left the
So yeah, [snorts] like the model will
learn to predict the next token which
implicitly requires it to know some
facts, know syntax and also maybe even
reason about what word should come next.
While this may like predicting next
token, you learn language, but
predicting next token ends up learning a
lot more and there's some evidence that
it ends up learning some notion of how
the world operates. So this is a very
nice example where we ask the model to
predict the next set of tokens. And here
the example is u pad watches a
demonstration of a bowling ball and a
leaf being dropped at the same time in a
vacuum cham chamber. Pat who is a
physicist predicts that and now the
model is asked to predict the next set
of tokens or the next set of words here.
And to predict these next set of words,
you implicitly have to understand what
the text was and in some way you have to
understand like how the world operates
as well to be able to answer. And it's
very interesting like if you change the
prompt like you'll get a different
behavior out of the model as well. The
point here being that language models
don't just learn syntax, don't just
learn words, but they learn a lot more
about how the world operates as well.
And similarly like we can ask them to do
math questions. We can ask them to
generate code. Um we can ask them they
have like fairly like reasonable medical
understanding as well. And more
importantly like we can start
transforming these models into
assistants now.
So the question now we'll get back to is
like okay pre-training gave us all that.
So how do we actually make this into
assistance?
So today's lecture we'll try to cover
roughly two or three kinds of techniques
to do so. First is instruction
fine-tuning, second is RLHF and third is
DPO and then we'll talk about some
limitations about what um is missing,
where are we going wrong and so on. All
right. So the first thing to understand
is when we pre-train models, we're
modeling language and yes that learns
more than language. learns an something
about the world, but that's still not
equivalent to assisting users. So, this
is an example from GPD3 um where the
prompt says explain the moon landing to
a six-year-old in few sentences and the
model completes it with what it thinks
should be the next set of tokens
according to the distribution of text it
has seen in its corpus. So, it starts
off explain the theory of gravity to a
six-year-old. Explain the theory of
relativity to a six-year-old in a few
sentences. And this isn't like this is
not what I expect my assistant to do.
It's just a language model predicting
the next token.
What we do wanted to do is actually give
an explanation or a story um where it
like a giant rocket ship blasted off the
earth carrying astronauts to the moon.
So some kind of an explanation which was
the original intent of the question and
not just the text it has seen on the
internet. And that's where the
discrepancy arises between language
modeling and assisting users.
The first set of techniques that were
developed for this was fine-tuning. And
we're going to talk a little bit about
this. So
the general paradigm even to this date
has been to first pre-train a language
model on a large corpus of text and then
fine-tune for your specific task. Um the
different so how does fine-tuning work?
You collect a set of inputs and you have
some target outputs and then you improve
the log likelihood of these target
outputs. So in this step two, you have
this input which was the movie was
something something and then you have
some target output which is good or bad
and the model learns to predict whether
the output was good or bad. And that's
really the main um difference between
fine-tuning and pre-training.
As we realized like I mean these
pre-training pre-trained models are good
for many many more things we started
scaling up the number of tasks we can
fine-tune on. So the previous example
was maybe something like sentiment
prediction but really these models can
be fine-tuned for many many different
tasks at the same time.
So broadly this can be seen as
collecting a set of instruction and
output pairs. So for example, if the
instruction is please answer the
following question, what is the boiling
point of nitrogen? Um we'll have some
answer like minus 320.4 and we want to
be able to predict this answer
conditioned on the input.
And once we collect a corpus of such
instruction output pairs, we can then
evaluate them on many many unseen tasks.
Can Jeffrey Hinton have a conversation
with George Washington? Give the
rational before answering. And the model
will produce a reasonable output here.
So
what if we fine-tune different scale
language models on many on the same kind
of corpus. So one thing that was
observed in a lot of prior work is that
as you increase the model parameter size
they actually start generalizing a lot
better. So even taking like a very small
corpus of such instruction output data
sets you start seeing a lot more
generalization. So to explain the table
a little bit, the big bench and MLU MLU
are like question answer pairs uh of the
kind you just saw in the previous slide.
And one thing to note here is that um
the bigger the parameters or larger the
model is the larger the gain is after
instruction fine-tuning.
So what this suggests us suggests to us
is that the models start like responding
and generalizing to questions even with
like very small corpus of data as well.
So to give an example of what the models
look before and after instruction
fine-tuning. It's fairly simple
question. In the following sentences
explain the [snorts] anticedent to the
pronoun and state that it is ambiguous.
So you get something which represents
more like the raw language model which
will start generating text on the right
side. The reporter and the chef will
discuss their favorite dishes and so on.
But after instruction fine-tuning it
will give us what the user perhaps
intended from the question
which is to give the correct answer.
Cool.
So instruction fine-tuning is fairly
simple. There's nothing surp
like do you see just reflect for
yourself. Do you see like some
limitations to something like this?
One limitation that obviously comes up
is that it's expensive to collect such
data. you have to collect um questions
and the labels for those questions and
that's hard like as you start increasing
the hardness of the questions there's
very few people who can answer those
questions so it's expensive to like
scale such data collections where the
humans have to sit down and write down
the answer to every question
but then if you look beyond that like
there are certain tasks which don't even
have a right answer so if I and this is
Like a lot of the use cases of language
models, like a lot of the use cases of
language models are creative. So if I
ask a language model to write a story
about a dog and her pet grasshopper,
there's no right answer for this. I
cannot sit down and say, "Oh, this is
the exact story I want to hear." Every
single time a person asks this question.
The second point is a little subtle, but
um in instruction fine-tuning, we have a
predefined answer. So the mistakes are
um penalized equally. So there's no good
or right answer. We don't we're not
necessarily saying like this was the
mistake. We are basically saying your
entire answer is wrong or your entire
answer is correct which is often not
necessarily true for um a specific
question.
So this is an example of this. If we
have a statement like Avatar is a
fantasy TV show, it's not that the
sentence entirely is correct or
incorrect, but it would have been better
to describe the Avatar as an adventure
TV show rather than a fantasy TV show.
I think this is like a problem that has
emerged recently is that the language
models truly are better at generating
answers that than humans.
So if we rely on humans to generate the
answers and generate the labels for our
questions, we are going to be limited by
how good the humans can answer the
question.
And finally, like one big mismatch is
that LM objectives um there's a bit of a
misalignment between what we want our
models to do, which is to engage well
with humans, um which is to like and
which is to follow their intent, whereas
our fine-tuning objective basically says
predict this answer really well. So
there's a little bit of an mismatch in
our training objective when we are doing
instruction fine-tuning.
Cool.
So this leads us to the paradigm of
reinforcement learning from human
preferences.
So the question is that um how much of
the improvement from instruction puning
comes from following a format or
actually teaching some new knowledge. I
think the most of the work suggests that
it actually is teaching largely
formatting. Um and most of the knowledge
actually comes from the base language
model itself and there's a very clear
way to do this. Um you can experiment
this by just teach training the model
wrong answers and it still does quite
well on the downstream tasks. Um so it
tells us that it's actually teaching
formatting more than the knowledge
itself.
The question was is are the um corpuses
always question answer format because
that's what we want out of chatbots. Um
not anymore. I think this was very early
days of LLM fine tuning and we were
focused more on like question answering
but it's the corpus for instruction fine
tuning are very very diverse. Now um
these LLMs are used for a wide variety
of tasks function calling tools and it's
not just assist like assistance like
means many different things. So it's not
question answers it could be just
anything.
Great. So now we'll like get into
reinforcement learning from human
preferences which addresses some of the
limitations
um which we discussed here.
So in throughout this like section,
we'll use summarization as an example
because there's not necessarily a good
summary that we can often train on. And
for notation, we'll assume that we are
given an instruction X and the language
model will generate some sample Y. And
our we'll pretend that we have a way for
a human to give us some kind of a reward
score for a given summary conditioned on
some input X and like summary Y. So we
have some news article which is San
Francisco, California, magnitude of 4.2
earthquake shook the San Francisco blah
blah blah. And we have one summary which
is earthquake hit San Francisco. There
was minor property damage but no
injuries. And we have another one which
is um Bay Area has good weather but it
is prone to earthquakes and wildfires.
Clearly one of the summaries is a little
better than the other. So let's say like
our reward function gives us a score of
8.0 and the other summary gets a score
of 1.2. Roughly speaking, we want to set
up the objective such that um we want to
maximize the expected reward. So
conditioned on some input instruction X,
we want our language model to generate
summaries Y such that the expected
reward will be high. Fairly simple
standard RL objective that you've
probably seen in the class before.
And this is like the core of how
chatbots are trained. And the rough
pipeline looks as the following which is
from the instruct GPD paper is that
we'll first do some instruction
fine-tuning. Um this is we collect some
demonstration data to condition like
just to get the formatting right as we
discussed earlier. Um second step and
the third step which we'll go a lot more
into is to set up how to like first get
a reward model which allows the mo uh us
to align with human intent and then we
maximize the reward model. So these are
the three steps we typically follow.
Great. So
let's just pretend for now that we have
a reward model where we want to maximize
this. And
yeah, like I'm presuming you all are
familiar with this gradient descent
idea. So yeah, the way we would change
the LM parameters to maximize this is
something you've seen before like some
form of gradient ascent. Usually there's
like more complicated optimizers but we
can pretend that is not required right
now. Um for now we'll just assume like a
generic RL formulation where uh we are
generating some sample S hat. So for
some distribution P theta S we want to
change the parameters theta um such that
the samples S hat are high reward under
the reward function R.
So the main issues and this is why like
we do RL is like our reward functions
are often non- differentiable. So if you
ask me to give a number my human mind is
not differentiable. So we cannot back
propagate through them. So this is why
we resort to RL.
So this is where policy gradient methods
that I think Chelsea has covered like
very early in the course come in is that
they allow us to maximize non-ifferiable
reward functions and we can estimate and
optimize this objective.
And I'll do a brief recap here because
it's important but and we'll slowly lead
into the RLHF pipeline as well but I'm
presume like um you have seen this
before. Great. So in this generic
objective when we want to estimate the
quantity that we want is the gradient of
the expected reward where we want the
samples S hat to have a high reward
under R. So this can be written down.
This is just algebra at this point where
the expectation can be written down as
the summation of R S multiplied by P
theta S and we have the gradient here.
So this is just a definition of
expectation and now we're going to like
propagate the gradient forward
simply by linearity of the gradient.
Um I assume you have seen this but I'm
going to go over this but this is a log
derivative trick which is we can rewrite
the gradient of p theta as p theta *
gradient of log p theta.
So to see that this is simply from the
chain rule is that the gradient of log p
theta simply can be written as 1 by p
theta and gradient multiplied by
gradients of p theta.
Cool. So we can rewrite this as to get
this identity where the gradient of P
theta can be rewritten as P theta
gradient log P theta.
Cool.
So the quantities in yellow is what we
want to substitute back.
And if we plug this back in, we get the
following equation, which is reward of
gradient of P theta is the same as
expectation under P theta R gradient of
log P theta.
All right. So why did we do all this?
Typically like when we're computing
expectation over sentences, it's really
not possible to enumerate every single
sentence possible. is just simply like
intractable to even try to do that. So
you want to be able to estimate the
gradient somehow and we want to be able
to create some kind of a stoastic
estimator so that we can get the
gradient out. So this log derivative
trick is what allows us to take this
gradient and convert it into an
expectation which we can sample and then
approximate.
And this is what we get as a final
result is that it's again an expectation
over reward multiplied by gradient of
log p theta.
So the question is um do we take this
gradient because we cannot back
propagate correctly. There's two reasons
really like first is we cannot set up an
objective where the reward we cannot
assume the reward is differentiable.
Second like which is the more precise
mathematical answer is that we are our
parameters are in the expectation.
So we do need to figure out a way to
take the gradients back to the
parameters in the expectation as well.
Yeah. But if our rewards were
differentiable, we don't necessarily
need to set our optimization objective
like this. We could imagine other
optimization objectives where we
directly back propagate end to end.
>> Okay. So um yeah so we went through all
the math just to show that like we can
rewrite the gradient of our original
objective and we can rewrite it as an
expectation again which we can now
approximate using Monte Carlo estimates
which is the equation on the end and we
can take this approximate gradient and
plug it into our favorite optimizer
which uses gradient descent or ascent
and that's really like this is just
supposed to be a brief recap. So yeah,
and it's a very intuitive objective as
well. So um really all it's saying is
that if for a certain sample the reward
is high, we should increase the log
likelihood. So if you
um the parameters are taking the
gradient in the direction of samples
which score high on the reward
and that's really all this objective
says. And if it's bad, you like take
directions opposite to those samples.
Cool. And yeah, this is why we call it
reinforcement learning because we're
doing good actions go there. Bad actions
don't go there. Uh the question is, am I
drawing full sentences or tokens? In
this context, we'll be drawing full
sentences. Yeah. Um the notation was set
up generally. So like we'll go back to
the XY notation again, but that was just
supposed to be a brief primer on policy
gradients.
Cool. So
first problem is that like we have so
far assumed that we have some kind of a
reward function which will tell us like
hey like the summary is 10.0 the other
is like 5.0 like is that usually is not
possible. Let's say you're training like
the biggest and the greatest LLM
possible and it needs like millions of
such queries and we're not going to have
an human army sit there and label every
answer. So it's not very scalable to ask
humans directly. So the general solution
towards this end has been to make
preference learning a separate
optimization problem where we try to
figure out a human reward model before
starting our RL optimization.
So
yeah, so we had two summaries and we
pretended the score was 8.0 and 1.2 and
we'll try to train on some kind of data
where we try to predict the score so
that we have a learned reward function
which we can later use in the RL.
Okay, so we talked about like we want to
learn this reward model and we have some
summaries where um you know like we want
to be able to predict their score. So
how do we like get these scores? So we
need some kind of an annotated data set.
Now the issue is that if we ask humans
for scores directly, two different
humans have completely different
calibration. So for a a score a summary
that has a score of seven would mean
something completely differently to two
humans. So there's not really an easy
way to aggregate. And even for the same
human, they would like probably score
the same summary differently at
different points depending on what they
ate for lunch or something. So it's not
really easy to get a score directly from
humans and if you ask them directly it's
it doesn't like work out very well. The
reward models you learn are not very
useful for training such language
models. So [snorts] the solution to this
is to not actually ask them for a score
but to actually ask them for
preferences. So we give them few
summaries and we just ask them hey do
you prefer this summary over this
summary or not and this is the kind of
annotated data set we should expect to
get collect for humans.
So now going a little bit deeper into
this. So we are going to collect a data
set of the form where we're given some
kind of an input X and we're going to be
given some kind of a winning summary
which is YW and we're going to be given
some kind of a losing summary Y L and
we're going to have some data set D for
this. And what we want to do is train a
reward model which assigns a higher
score to the winning summaries and
assigns a lower score to the losing
summaries. So the optimization objective
which is called the Bradley Terry
objective is a way of going from such
data set of preferences to an implicit
reward score which would align with the
preferences.
And the way we train this is we minimize
this log sigmoid and the difference of
reward
assigned to the winning and the losing
summary. So
yeah, all this objective is saying is
that a reward model should make sure the
reward for the correct summary is higher
than the reward of the losing summary.
So the question is like is it unbounded
or do you um normalize this? Um the
actual issue that arises which is this
is actually a very important observation
that we'll actually use to develop DPO
as well. um the objective just asks the
difference to be high. So the difference
will be high even if you assign a reward
of,000 and 10,000 or it'll be high even
if you assign a difference from 1 to
999. There's no real like scaling here
which allows that. So yeah, typically
you have to do some kind of post talk
normalization to make sure that
different prompts get rewards at the
same scale. Otherwise like the
optimization objective can get a little
wonky.
Um but yeah this is the Bradley Terry
objective which allows us to go from a
data set of preferences to a reward
model which we'll use in our lecture.
Yeah the question is is that why we take
the sigmoid? Um not really. There's a
few different functions you can set up.
um sigmoid just like maps naturally to
like the probability of this sample
winning over this sample. So yeah,
that's why it's typically used as a
sigmoid. But really all we want to
encourage is that the reward model
should like the difference should be
high.
All right. Um so now we get back to our
RL loop and what do we have? We have
some kind of an instruction tuned model.
Let's say PPD. We have learned some kind
of a reward model using the Bradley
objective which gives us a scalar
output. So it takes an input X gives us
a summary and then gives us a scalar
output RM 5 X Y. Now
okay so this is the simple part in some
ways. We're going to do the RLHF loop
here. And the way we're going to do this
is we want to optimize the expected
reward as we started with where we're
going to plug in our LLM parameters in
the expectation for P theta. Uh so it
will produce some kind of a summary yhat
conditioned on some input X and our
reward model is going to be the learned
reward model from preferences.
Before I move on like I have a question
which is slightly hard. I started off
saying that the reward functions are
non- differentiable and that's part of
why we want to do RL but we just learned
a reward model and we know like we
typically learn a reward model using
neural networks themselves and they are
like very much differentiable we can do
back propagate through them so why are
we doing RL that's the right answer so
um the token like we're outputting
discrete tokens and when we assume we
can back propagate things we cannot
actually back propagate through the
discrete language tokens.
So even if we have a reward model that
is differentiable, we generate some
output, we plug it into our reward model
and then we want to go back directly to
the parameters of the language model. Um
but we get this discrete bottleneck in
the middle where we cannot back
propagate our gradients from the reward
model to the samp uh to the language
model. And that's the reason why like we
again have to resort to RL even though
we have a differentiable non-b blackbox
reward model here. But yeah, good
attempts everyone like these are close.
Yeah. Um so let's say like we have a
reward model RM5 X Yhat.
Um let's assume like y is a continuous
variable or like so typically we'll take
some input we'll generate some output
we'll plug it into a reward learned
reward model and if everything is a
continuous function here you can rely on
back propagation to take the gradients
um and update the model parameters such
that the reward model score keeps going
up. So you don't actually need to do RL
and not doing RL is often very good
because it's expensive to do because of
the sampling. But the issue is that our
Y hat here are discrete tokens. So
they're sampled from some underlying
distribution and once you include the
sampling operation, it's very hard to
like there are tricks to do that but
they're not very stable but it's hard to
like back propagate through there. Yes.
So I didn't want to assume like gumball
softmax is known to people here but like
gumball softmax unfortunately like so
far hasn't scaled super well especially
like now the language so to
contextualize this yhat is a sentence
which could be thousands and thousands
of tokens and each token vocabulary
sizes are on the order of hundreds of
thousands of um tokens so it's
yeah the entire sentence is a
combinatorial space of like 100,000
tokens multiplied by the sequence length
Um, Gumba Softmax usually doesn't scale
beyond like thousand dimensions or so
on. Yeah,
cool. This is a hard question. So, I
like I wanted to like touch upon this
because you should never assume that you
need to do RL.
Um, so yeah.
All right. So um
one issue like even when we set up this
objective is that and somebody alluded
to this was that our reward models are
never perfect. So we don't want to
assume that like they'll give us a
perfect score. After all they have been
like fit to human preferences on a
certain distribution. We don't want to
assume that they'll give us a good score
for every single input and output. So,
and if you do naive optimization like we
described so far, you will get models
which hack the reward model and we'll
see some plots for that later as well.
So, one another thing we add is
something called the KL penalty or the
callback library divergence. And what
the kale penalty basically says is um so
it's added to the reward where we have
beta log p theta by p pre-trained. So p
theta is the quantity we are optimizing
right now. This is the language model
which is currently assigning the
probabilities to token yhat and pp
trained is the model we started with. So
it could be instruction fine-tuned and
these are the probabilities under those
model and roughly speaking whenever a
probability distribution deviates from
the pre-trained distribution we get a
penalty. So we get a lower score if we
are deviating too much from the
pre-trained model.
And if you work out the math, this thing
is exactly the KL divergence between our
distribution or our language model that
we are optimizing right now and the
language model we started with.
And the reason why we want to do this is
that um as I said like the reward model
is imperfect. we know it's more accurate
on a distribution of preferences that we
trained on and we want to make sure the
model stays close to where it started
off from.
So this is one of the first examples of
like RLHF where um it worked quite well.
So this is the summarization task itself
and we are the curve basically the
x-axis is the model size and the y-axis
is how often is the summary preferred
over some ground truth summary
um for some news articles and if you
look at the blue curve it's the
pre-training curve which as the model
size increases the fraction of summaries
preferred over the baseline increases
and then you have SFD or instruction
finetuning which gives an improvement
over the U pre-trained model. But when
you look at the RL curve, this is the
first model which actually exceeds the
human written summaries.
So now we are generating summaries even
at a small size which are preferred over
human summaries and that's this is like
one of the earlier results in RHF which
shows like the power of optimizing for
preferences directly.
So the question is like are there models
for human preferences which are not just
binary and like account for like fuzzy?
I think this is a very like hard
question which like goes into um so it
is known that human preferences can
often be intransitive. So what do I mean
by that is like let's say we prefer A
over B then we prefer B over C and then
we prefer C over A. This doesn't make
any sense. Um because ideally if you
prefer A over B and B over C, you should
prefer A over C. But we get lots of
scenarios where humans prefer A over C
as well. Um and you will unfortunately
observe some noise in the data like that
where the preferences in fact the
preferences we observe in real life are
like very very noisy. Um and I don't
think we have like a great solution for
this. um to give to like even ground
this preference learning is a binary
classification task. We're just trying
to predict like which sample is winning.
So it's a binary classification task. So
you like most binary classification
tasks you can reach an accuracy of like
90% 95%. But for most of our language
model and reward models we reach an
accuracy of like 65 to 70%. So we're
barely doing better than chance. Um but
even that is still like enough to like
give us like pretty large improvements
in performance. The question is like
what changed to make this
differentiable? Um we did not make
anything differentiable. The that's the
reason why we started doing RL is to
like be able to take the policy gradient
like this estimator this does not
require us to be able to yeah so that
just requires the gradient to be like
with the log probabilities of the model.
it does not back propagate into the
reward at all. So the question is like
what if the P theta RL is less than P
theta PD and like wouldn't that
encourage the model to go in those
directions. Um it's good to know. So
this is like the expectation is broken
down here into more explicitly but it's
good to know a property about KL
divergence that is always greater than
equal to zero. I'll leave that as an
exercise for you to like prove that but
like so the penalty is always positive.
So the question is are there in
intelligent ways to choose prompts such
that we get preferences over um things
that the model is bad at? Um that's a
great question. Yeah like so um there
are works which try to look into it. Um
this like touches upon active
exploration. you want to get preference
signal explicitly where the model is
confused right so I think there's things
which touch upon like we want to
maximize information gain such that the
model will learn the best um is there a
wellestablished standard I don't think
so but this is like a good problem to
look into okay I will start with direct
preference optimization next so if
there'll be a little bit more math but
it's very fun So we're going to talk a
little bit about direct preference
optimization.
So the RLF pipeline I described some of
you might find it complex or some of you
might find it easy but in practice when
we try to do this at very large scale
models it can be quite expensive.
So
let's say you're like training a 100red
billion parameter model, maybe a
trillion parameter model. You have to
sample every answer and then query your
reward model and depending on the RL
algorithm you use. Um
you
you have to compute like value functions
and like other things just to optimize
the model. And you don't have to
understand this figure. I put it
specifically to scare you guys. Um, so
here like there's just like a whole flow
of things that in practice can be fairly
hard to get right and the more
parameters you have in the system, the
harder it is to get it right.
So RLHF can be pretty complex. But
so when we were looking into diet
preference optimization, our goal was to
like can we like make this a lot
simpler? And
yeah as I said like they have some
initial pipeline which we fit an RM we
like take an instruction tune model and
produce a final RL model but if you look
at the whole process like we have a
language model and we're collecting some
preferences why can we just not directly
like train on the preference data and
directly optimize the parameter models
why do we have to like learn this like
intermediate quantity like a reward
model And why can't we just directly go
from preferences and optimize our
language model? So that's really why
it's called direct preference
optimization is that we find a way to go
from preferences to and optimizing the
language model. And the way we do it is
that at a very high level we want to be
able to write the reward model in terms
of our language model itself. Why do we
want to do that? Because we fit our
reward model to the preference data
through a fairly simple classification
loss, the Bradley Terry loss we
discussed. If we can just connect the
reward model and the language model
instead of like having a separate
process, we can just take the language
model parameters and fit it to the loss
through the loss directly. And that's
really like the highle motivation for
direct preference optimization.
Yeah.
So
this part of the math gets a little bit
um slightly intense. So like I'll go
through this slowly. Okay. So we
discussed the scale constrained RL
objective in the last few slides where
we want to maximize the expected reward
with some scale penalty such that the
model should not drift away from the
instruction fine-tuned model a lot. So
this again the parameters we're going to
optimize is P theta RL P pre-trained and
RM are fixed and for now we can like
yeah we're just assuming some kind of
reward model here. It turns out that
this equation actually has a closed form
solution. Um and this is not possible if
you're doing just the regular expected
reward maximization. But once you add a
KL constraint, it turns out that you can
write out a closed form solution to this
equation which is really cool. like it's
rare to find such things and the
solution looks something like this. This
is the optimal policy P star where we're
going to compute probabilities over Yhat
conditioned over X and roughly this
optimal quantity says that we want
ignore the ZX for now. Uh we have our
pre-trained model P pre-trained Yhat
given X and we're going to multiply the
log probabilities with the um
exponentiated reward.
So
what very simply put like exponentiated
so if a sentence has a higher reward so
if a y hat has a higher reward we're
going to upweight the probabilities
under the uh optimal distribution by an
exponentiated reward by beta higher
reward high exponent higher probability
under the optimal policy if the reward
is low it's going to be downweighted
by exponential reward as
and zx here is just a normalizing factor
which ensures that this quantity is a
probability distribution. So really you
only need to focus on the numerator and
that's it. You'll have to take my word
for that this is the optimal uh solution
for the above equation. Uh maybe I can
share something later on like how to
derive this. Um but yeah
cool. Now this is like where the key
observation comes in is that because we
have this optimal solution to the above
equation we can rewrite the reward model
in terms of the optimal policy itself.
So this lower equation is just like a
rearrangement of the terms. Um the
reward model can rmx comma yhat can be
written as beta log p star upon ppdt
and we have some beta log zx term which
is a constant
over y. So again just to like make sure
this makes sense intuitively as well. If
a completion yhat should have a high
score it will typically have a high
probability under p star as well. And
PPD is something that's fixed. So beta
log will be high whenever the reward
model gives a high score.
And similarly like if a reward model
assigns a poor score to Yhat, our
optimal policy will typically assign a
low log pro a low probability to Yhat
and typically the B beta log P star by
PT will also be low. So the relationship
sort of makes sense and we can ignore ZX
for now. Cool.
The main argument here is that
this isn't just true for the optimal
policy. You can always plug in some
reward model P theta and it will be
optimal for some kind of reward model.
And that's really like the observation
you make here. And yeah so we have just
replaced P star with some kind of a
learnable policy given that our
parameters theta represent the optimum
policy for some kind of a reward model
and after that it's simple like given
the relationship we've derived so far we
know this is how we fit our reward model
through the Bradley Terry loss where we
want to make sure that the reward for
the winning completion is higher than
the reward for the losing completion
and
So far, I've been asking you to ignore
the partition function, but that was for
a reason. Um, the reason is that because
the objective only optimizes for the
difference between the rewards, the
partition function ZX just simply
cancels out.
So, um, maybe I can write this out on
the board.
We started with the relation rm theta x
comma yw
and
we had beta log
p theta y w given x where yw is the
winning completion
and pd
yw given X.
Yeah.
So this is the relation we used with
beta log ZX and we're going to rewrite
the same thing for the losing completion
as well. So X comma Y L beta log
P of theta which is the current
parameters we're optimizing. Y L is our
losing completion conditioned on the
input X divided by the P the log
probabilities under the pre-trained
model Y L conditioned on X and beta log
ZX.
Now notice that like the reward model is
like the input is the same to the reward
model. So we're using the same text and
we're summarizing the same text. So the
input is actually the same. So when
we're going to subtract this, we're
going to subtract these and this and
this is just simply going to cancel out.
The reason why canceling out of this is
important is that ZX is actually
intractable to compute. It's not
something we can compute for real. So we
get this relation that you can see over
here is the difference between the
reward models is simply the difference
between the beta log ratios here.
Cool. So taking this identity which we
have just derived, we simply plug it
into the original Bradley Terry loss and
we get something super nice is that um
we'll have a data set of again input
winning output losing output and we're
going to optimize this objective
directly for the language model
parameters.
And this is a classification objective
by the way. So we're not doing any RL
loop anymore. We are going directly from
the preference data set and optimizing
the language parameter models
themselves.
Yes. So initially like they'll be the
same but the gradient would only back
propagate through the um p thetas. PPD
will remain the same throughout and it
will increase the probability of the
winning completion and decrease the
probability of the losing completion. So
let's let's let's spend a little bit of
time here again. Um this objective will
try to encourage the RM theta for the
winning completion to go up and RM theta
for the losing completion to go down
by the way to increase RM theta is to
increase the probability of YW under the
current model and decrease the
probability of the losing one under the
current model. It's a very intuitive
objective right like good thing go up
bad thing go down. Um and apparently you
can do it without RL or like any like
complexity.
So the question is can we do something
like distillation without um instead of
this the question is like um so for the
reward model like you first have to get
a reward model somehow right no one's
there's no like easy way to get it so
you have to collect some kind of
preference data to even begin with to
get a reward model and that's where DPO
comes in is that like if you have
collected a preference data instead of
fitting an explicit reward model you can
optimize their language model parameters
directly.
Yeah. So the question is like there's a
penalty for pre-trained model. We're not
drifting too far from the pre-trained
model. Actually this does do that. So
this is this is a good question. So
[snorts]
we our loss function is set up as a log
sigmoid. So one property with a sigmoid
is that the gradients vanish when the
difference becomes is already
sufficiently large and the difference
becomes sufficiently large like faster
than the so the beta parameter actually
controls how quickly the difference
becomes large. So if you have a very
high beta even a small discrepancy would
like suddenly saturate the sigmoid and
it will not change the parameters a lot.
The question is, is the main advantage
of DPO that you don't have to train a
reward model? Um, the way I would say it
is that you are training a reward model
because you're using the same objective.
The DPO provides a connection between
the reward model and the corresponding
optimal policy for it. So you don't have
to do an explicit RL loop to go from the
reward model to a optimal policy for it.
You can all we have cleverly
parameterized a reward model in terms of
the language model itself.
So when you fit a reward model to the
preference data, you are optimizing the
language model itself too. So the
question is do we still need to do RLF
or not given like this is like cheaper.
Um I think it depends a lot on
situation. I think there's still some
perpetrated benefits to RHF because you
can expect like some kind of
generalization from the reward model
which allows you to grade generations
which might not have been seen in
preference data. So there's still some
benefit to it. So it depends upon your
budget and like what you want to
achieve.
So the question I get like is that the
KL divergence like why are we relying on
the sigmoid when like initially like the
KL divergence was not related to the
sigma
>> to be more clear or precise I think it's
the beta term which controls like how
fast how much you're allowed to drift
away and even in the original RL
objective
um this beta term is what controls pulls
the divergence between allowed
divergence between our current model and
the pre-trend model. So if the beta is
really high, you are not allowed to
diverge at all because you'll be
penalized a lot more. Yes. So like the
beta controls the strength or the weight
on this divergence. That's a good
question. Yeah. Um so [snorts] there's
two kinds of sampling involved right
now. First we want to like create a
preference data set where humans label
their preferences and then during the RL
optimization itself um we want to sample
to get a score under some kind of an
external or like explicit reward model
and then we score and then we optimize.
So we are taking care of the second
sampling step but the first sampling
step is still needed. Yeah that's a good
question. So um when you're doing online
RL or like some kind of RLE procedure
you can you don't only need the prompts
you don't need um a preference data set.
So typically the set of prompts which is
used during RL is larger than the set of
prompts you use during preference
training. Yeah that's a good question.
So like I think the question basically
tries to ask like do we can we take into
account the strength of the preference
and not just like a binary label. Um I
think this is a limitation for both RLHF
and DPU I think. Um and we should so
giving more insight typically like when
we collect preference data sets we ask
annotators to like give a strength for
their preferences and we only keep the
preferences which are strong. So
typically the pref but this isn't a
resolved problem. How to learn from
noisy data and like low preferences or
high strength preferences like still an
undersolved problem.
And yeah like these are some of the
results for direct preference
optimization.
Um we showed like a theoretical
equivalence between doing the DPO
objective and doing a KL constrained RL
procedure. And in practice when we try
to look at the summarization task and
try to measure win rates like we were
doing earlier, we do actually find that
like it does similar or better. But this
is like a debatable question. So like
yeah but like in general it does pretty
well the beta parameter that um
do you see this beta parameter here that
corresponds exactly to the beta
parameter in the which is the extra
hyperparameter there. So I'm just going
to summarize like what we have learned
so far um and then we'll move on to like
where things are missing and so on.
We want to optimize for human
preferences because um first of all it's
like more aligned with the objectives.
We want the way we use these models are
more closely aligned with like improving
human engagement or like satisfying
human preferences. So we want to
optimize for that directly as well. And
instead of relying on unccalibrated
scores from different annotators, we try
to collect preferences and then learn a
reward model of some form either through
DPO or through RLHF and improve the
model through that.
Um, in RLHF we learn an explicit reward
model which gives an explicit score for
every completion we sample and we use
that to optimize the language model
parameters. And we typically impose some
kind of KL constraint to make sure that
our model does not drift too far from
where it was initialized.
It's very effective, maybe sometimes
even more effective than DPO, but can be
a little tricky to get right and it's
computationally expensive because of the
sampling procedure that needs to be
done.
And in direct preference optimization,
we can completely skip the sampling part
and optimize directly on the preference
data by posing it as a binary
classification problem.
Cool. And it's very simple and effective
and does not require an online step. So
where does this all lead us? Like we've
like discussed all the RLHF and DPO
stuff and like these are roughly how the
chatbots are built by the way. So um
this is the instruct GPD pipeline. This
was like one of the first like
instruction like first chat bots which
was available to public and interact
they interacted with it and it worked
pretty well like it um it can do a lot
of tasks. It can answer general purpose
questions and [snorts] yeah
instruct GPD like this is a comparison
between what the pre-trained model gives
as an answer versus what an instruction
tuned or an RLF model gives us an answer
and yeah these are some examples
and yeah we can we have optimized these
models for dialogue and like we can it's
not just summaries I want to say like we
You can optimize them for many many
general purpose tasks. And the more data
you collect, more tasks you cover, the
better these models are going to do, the
better they're going to understand the
intent and the better they're going to
like respond to like all of our needs.
And yeah, DPO's been used a lot in the
open source community ever since it was
launched. Um it's fairly cheap works.
It's pretty performant and at some point
like all LLMs were using DPO to like get
their alignment with human feedback.
Llama and Mistl models if you've heard
of them were also like post trained
using DPO. So yeah
and I guess like this is an interesting
example where it's it's this is it's a
good question to ask like what is the um
difference between instruction tune
model and RLHF models and like one clear
stylistic difference that emerges is
that they tend to give more detailed
answers well formatted answers and they
tend to like align more with the kind of
test text that humans find easier to
read. So the question here are like what
are the five most common causes of
stress among people and if you just do
instruction fine-tuning with a very
small data set you get a good answer.
The five most common causes of stress
among people are work money
relationships health and a family but
then you do some kind of a PO procedure
you get a much clearer longer answer
with like a very well formatted list and
these are all emergent properties. This
is what the model has discovered that
humans like and prefer and that's why
they tend to generate answers of that
form. I I love the question. I'll um
basically like I I'll I had a slide on
this um towards the end but yes the
question is like do can we trust like
people's feedback and what do we do if
like people don't know what they want?
Um again that's a very like hard
boundary to go to and I think what
happens is that like there's a
misalignment between short-term
incentives and long-term incentives.
There are certain behaviors which look
good in short term and people give
feedback based on short-term incentives
but sometimes behaviors are these are
very undesirable in the long term and
that is truly an hard problem to solve
within the RLHF pipeline. It's a good
question. The question is like can do we
do they rank like two answers or
multiple answers and do we train on NC2
pairs or um yeah so I think like yeah
you can roughly like just for efficiency
purposes people typically rank more than
one answer and you get more learning
data out of it that way because you get
NC2 pairs preference pairs but you can
there's something called the placket
loose family which is like a
generalization of Bradley Terry that
allows you to directly train on ranked
completions as well beyond just
preference players too. So you can do
either of those. They probably both work
fine. Yeah, that's a really good
question. So I think like our companies
incentivized to like give preferences to
like engagement which are not aligned
with human. Um this goes well beyond the
scope of this lecture and like be like I
don't know like what I can say about
this but we can look back at history,
right? So this is not an issue that was
just true for LMS. For example, YouTube
had a lot of issues with like
recommendation systems and people were
engaging with YouTube way more than they
wanted it to. So in some ways like this
is a broader problem which like on how
technology should be interfaced with
people and societies. But [snorts] if I
briefly recall from that incident um is
that it was actually in YouTube's
incentive to make sure that the
consumers have long-term healthy
engagement.
So which means like in if they're like
spending 20 hours a day on YouTube,
that's probably not good for the product
as well. So they probably want to make
sure that they're not spending way too
much time. Um, so if you do optimize for
long-term engagement, that should
ideally address that should not fall to
like the syopantic behaviors that we saw
from GPD40 because that that is more
short-term behavior.
But yeah,
cool. Um
and yeah like I this is basically all
we've talked about and I just I wanted
to bring up like a couple of things that
this is let me just jump ahead to this
slide where because we've already talked
about it is that this is a very like
fast evolving topic. This is touching
our lives right now when we are deciding
how like to interface chat bots with um
humans. And
if for people who might not be familiar
with this incident, but like GPD40
became fairly psychopantic due to a
model update that was pushed and
suddenly it was like endorsing all good
and bad ideas from their users in a way
that everyone deemed was unhealthy. So I
don't work at OpenAI and I'm not making
any comments but like um these issues
like these are very real and we're still
trying to understand how does our
feedback data affect our final models
emergent behaviors and this like affects
how we use our products as well. And
yeah, like a lot of great questions came
up in the class and those are like
active problems people are working on
and we don't necessarily have the
answers to all of them. So you guys
should go look more into it.
Yeah. And the other main thing that I do
wanted to touch upon like which is a
limitation of the current paradigm is
that there's this phenomena of reward
hacking which again touches upon
misalignment as well is that when we
train on these learned reward models
they do align with human preferences up
to a certain point but as you train
progressively against them they tend to
start drifting away from what we truly
want. So it's a very common problem in
RL when you have proxy rewards instead
of true rewards that you care award care
about and this is generally true for
machine learning as well. Um so yeah
this affects like ability to scale
reinforcement learning too because if
you start hacking you have to stop
training at some point and it this this
is like an active optimization problem
that people are trying to address. Yeah
I think the field is evolving quite a
lot. So like it goes beyond like people
are moving towards more rubric based
things where we score them for several
different aspects.
Um but yes like you typically do want to
collect many different kinds of data to
teach the model like what kind of
behaviors we want to instill and how
what's the right way to respond to
certain situations. It's very hard to
cover every situation a chatbot might
ever encounter. So we are relying on the
model to generalize from what kind of
data we're teaching. But it these things
break all the time and there's certain
unexpected behaviors that come out of
these models uh in ways where we could
not anticipate.
Yeah, I've already touched a little bit
upon this but like it's a very fast
evolving field very like many many areas
still to improve. um preference data is
still expensive to collect and like it
as we have maybe discussed like it's not
necessarily like representative of what
kind of model behaviors we want. So we
are looking for better ways to like
improve the feedback. Um,
I think you listen to a lot more about
very cool evolving things in reasoning
space where the models are generating
their own outputs from and are being
graded by verifiable rewards. And that's
like one of the coolest topics we're
looking at as well in post- training and
reasoning as well. And
something that I personally find very
interesting is that like language models
are aligned to the aggregate preferences
of humans. like we are interacting
oneonone like we're not interacting with
the entire internet. So we do want to
eventually make sure that the models are
aligned to our needs and not just
everybody's needs. So personalizing
language models and having more
contextual input about us and our
preferences is something that's also a
fairly nice evolving field. And yeah, we
talked a little bit about hallucinations
and like uncontrolled emergent behaviors
and these are all still active problems
we like to work on.
And that's all for today.